<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm.ta">Routledge</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">Routledge</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Routledge</journal-id>

<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Routledge</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>

<issn pub-type="ppub"></issn>
<issn pub-type="epub"></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Taylor and Francis Group</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>

<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">15031-5034fr4</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4324/9781003009498-15031-5034fr4</article-id>

<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Digital Marketing Excellence</subject>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>SIXTH EDITION</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>

<title-group>
<article-title>Planning, Optimizing and Integrating
Online Marketing</article-title>
</title-group>

<contrib-group>

<contrib contrib-type="author1">
<name>
<surname>Chaffey</surname>
<given-name>Dave</given-name>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"></xref>
</contrib>

<contrib contrib-type="author2">
<name>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<given-name>PR</given-name>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"></xref>
</contrib>

<aff id="aff1">
<address-line>Cover design and illustration by davymac.com,Sixth edition published 2023 ,by Routledge ,4Park Square, Milton Park, Abingdon, Oxon, OX14 4RN,and by Routledge ,605 Third Avenue, New York, NY 10158</address-line>
</aff>

</contrib-group>


<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2023</year>
</pub-date>

<permission>
<copyright-statement>&#x00A9; 2023 Dave Chaffey and PR Smith</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
<ali><p>The right of Dave Chaffey and PR Smith to be identified as authors of this
work has been asserted in accordance with sections 77 and 78 of the Copyright,Designs and Patents Act 1988.</p>
<p>All rights reserved. No part of this book may be reprinted or reproduced or
utilised in any form or by any electronic, mechanical, or other means, now known or hereafter invented, including photocopying and recording, or in any
information storage or retrieval system, without permission in writing from the publishers.</p>
<p>Trademark notice: Product or corporate names may be trademarks or registered trademarks, and are usedonly for identification andexplanation without intent to infringe.</p>
<p>First edition published by Butterworth Heinemann / Elsevier 2001 Fifth edition published by Routledge 2017</p>
<p>British Library Cataloguing-in-Publication Data
A catalogue record for this book is available from the British Library</p>
<p>Library of Congress Cataloging-in-Publication Data A catalog record has been requested for this book
ISBN: 978-0-367-44401-3 (hbk)
ISBN: 978-0-367-44475-4 (pbk)
ISBN: 978-1-003-00949-8 (ebk)</p>
</ali>
</permission>

<self-uri content-type="uri" xlink:href="15031-5034fr4.pdf"/>
<abstract>
<p>
</p>
</abstract>

<kwd-group>
<kwd>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</kwd>
<kwd>polyol metabolism</kwd>
<kwd>sorbitol dehydrogenase</kwd>
</kwd-group>

<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta> <meta-name>access-type</meta-name>
<meta-value>free</meta-value> </custom-meta> </custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>

<body>
<title>Digital Marketing Excellence</title>
<p>Now in its sixth edition, the hugely popular Digital Marketing Excellence is a practical guide to creating and executing integrated digital marketing plans, combining established approaches to marketing planning with the creative use of new digital models and digital tools.</p>
<p>Written by two highly experienced digital marketing consultants, the book shows you how to:</p>
<sec id="S1">
<title>Digital Marketing In Context</title>
<p>Digital Marketing = Marketing</p>
<p>Digital marketing doesn&#x2019;t happen in isolation; indeed many have said that, today, digital marketing is marketing because of the dramatic growth inadoption of digital devices, digital communications and E-commerce sales we have experienced over the last 30 years. With the majority of business to consumer (B2C) and business to business (B2B) purchases involving digital touchpoints, we believe it&#x2019;s essential that businesses invest in dedicated resources, plan-ning and optimization for digital marketing. It&#x2019;s also essential for marketers to develop specific digital marketing skills.</p>
<p>In Chapter 1 we highlight the vital role of digital marketing within marketing and how it relates to the broader context of global challenges. We start by highlighting the growth in Purpose-Driven Marketing along with the emergence of stakeholder capitalism (and stakeholder marketing). We introduce the Virtuous Circle of Insights-Driven Marketing to show how businesses can compete if they adopt the right mindset. This chapter explains digital marketing jargon to clarify key digital marketing concepts from lifecycle marketing to digital transformation and the &#x201C;post-digital world&#x201D;. Finally, we introduce PR Smith&#x2019;s SOSTAC&#x00AE; Planning methodology explaining how you can create a more strategic approach to creating and integrating digital plans (which is detailed in Chapter 10) to deliver the 5S benefits of digital marketing.</p>

<p><bold>Why does digital marketing demand dedicated resources and plans?M</bold></p>
<p>Digital marketing should be integrated with traditional marketing since it needs to support the same goals and most customers will experience both. However, digital marketing is complex and requires careful planning, analysis and implementation to be effective. That&#x2019;s the reason behind the popularity of <italic>Digital Marketing Excellence: Planning, Optimizing, Automating and Integrating Online Marketing</italic>. Now in its sixth edition, it has been used as a core text on many digital marketing diplomas and university modules because it is dedicated to digital marketing and explains how marketing and digital goals and strategy must work together.</p>
<p>Yet, some say we are in a post-digital world, so we must ask you one simple question, which others may ask you: &#x201C;why bother?&#x201D; Why bother with digital marketing? It&#x2019;s so fast changing, sometimes complicated and often confusing, that we forget the only reason why we build a website, an app, a bot, a product, a service, an experience or evena business. The answer is &#x201C;to help customersbetter than competitors.&#x201D; Plus, to gain awareness, encourage purchase and deliver quality customercare, it&#x2019;s essential to be visible online to complete. Keep this close to your heart as you progress through your career. Sometimes technology&#x2019;s functional potential is so exciting that we forget why we are doing it in the first place. . . &#x201C;to help customers&#x201D; or &#x201C;to help stakeholders&#x201D; (like the communities we live in andthe planet we live on). The ongoing popularity of digital transformation programmes amongst larger businesses 30 years plus since the invention of the web shows that businesses have found it challenging to adapt to the speed of change and still need to refinetheir approaches to managing and integrating. If we were truly in a post-digital world there would be noneed for transformation programmes.</p> 

<p><bold>The most exciting time to work in marketing?</bold></p>
<p>There is no doubt that this is the most exciting time to work in marketing as what we can now do withdigital techniques like Artificial Intelligence (AI)and Virtual Reality (VR) would have been considered magic 20 years ago. We will see in Chapter 2 that there are literally thousands of marketing technology (MarTech) options to help us automate and personalize customer communications and capture and analyse data. But we have to select the best options, considerthe integration of data and question the return on investment of using these tools. Some of the many MarTech choices are shown in Figure 1.1, which summarizes how 30 different categories of marketing softwarearound the edge of the wheel can support marketersinachieving their customer lifecycle goals and KPIsshown at the centre of the wheel. For each of the 30categories we have selected five options that are someof the most widely used tools with those towardsthe edge of the wheel typically offering low-costor free options, with more sophisticated, enterpriseversionstowards the centre of the wheel. At the end of Chapter 3, we show how to simplify more complex MarTech stacks into a MarTech spine.</p>

<fig fig-type="figure" id="F1.1" position="float">
<label>FIGURE 1.1</label>
<caption>The MarTech Wheel - a summary of marketing technologies to support lifecycle marketing activities.</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="Fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Throughout the book we will explore all the majortechnology developments in marketing.As marketers become more data-driven and insights-driven and more analytical, we can measure,quantify and calculate thereturn on investment (ROI) on just about everything we do.This opens the boardroom door wide for marketers to step in and justify why they need more resources to integrate their digital marketing to align with marketing goals.</p>
<p>Increasing use of MarTech and AI should also loosen up our thinking and encourages more room for creative thinking and more room for insight-driven decisions. We also have the challenge of keeping up-to-date practices and selecting the best options from themarketing techniques available from the digital platforms like the search engines and social networks.</p>
<p><bold>Post-COVID marketing</bold></p>
<p>The COVID pandemic has affected us all and significantly changed the lives of hundreds of millions of people directly and indirectly. COVID has prompted us all to reflect on our neigh-bours locally and globally. As marketers and business people, we are reviewing how we operate and work. The pandemic has prompted the use of remote working, virtual meeting and events that need to be supported by digital marketing activities. Within B2B sectors marketing, pro-fessional development has been supported by huge increases in engagement as suggested by the B2B webinar platform BrightTALK (Figure 1.2).</p>
<p>It&#x2019;s positive that the rich content available through digital platforms can support professional development goals as summarized by BrightTALK (2021) as we hope to support readers through this book and its online resources. Top-rated reasons for using these platforms for professional development were:</p>
<p>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>To keep up to date with what&#x2019;s happening in your industry 67%</list-item>
<list-item>To improve the quality of the work you do 65%</list-item>
<list-item>To acquire a new body of knowledge or skills 63%</list-item>
<list-item>To discover new things 61%</list-item>
<list-item>For the joy of learning 46%</list-item>
<list-item>To innovate 45%</list-item>
<list-item>To solve an organizational problem/issue 38%</list-item>
<list-item>For inspiration 37%</list-item>
<list-item>To increase your qualification for a desired job 34%</list-item>
<list-item>To become compliant to industry standards 30%</list-item>
<list-item>To learn to do your job 29%</list-item>
<list-item>To maintain your accreditation 24%</list-item>
<list-item>To qualify for a promotion 18%</list-item>
<list-item>To solve a personal problem 13% </list-item>
</p>
<fig fig-type="figure" id="F1.2" position="float">
<label>FIGURE 1.2</label>
<caption>Growth in online webinar communities</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="Fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Beyond COVID, there are other crises affecting our markets and our lives including the Climate Emergency and a potential AI crisis, which we&#x2019;ll explore later. We have responsibilities as marketers to be aware of these crises, to discuss them, to influence them and ensure we do not cast away our markets, our marketing skills and our humanity as we need to embrace human-centred marketing. Hopefully the profound importance of this will prevail as the drive for growth establishes new markets, eventually on new planets.</p>

<p><bold>Accelerated change</bold></p>
<p>We are entering a period of unprecedented change.Ray Kurzweil&#x2019;s Law of Accelerating Returns, explored in Chapter 9, observed that the rate of progress during 1980-2000 was five times faster than theaverage rate of progress during the 20th century andthat another 20th-century&#x2019;s worth of progresshappened between 2000 and 2014 and that another 20th-century&#x2019;s worth of progress will happen by 2021. A couple of decades later, this scale of progress will happen multiple times in the same year and, even later, in less than one month. We know accelerated change is occurring; we&#x2019;re just not sure exactly how it will manifest itself. Look very carefully at AI and keep a very open mind and a very creative mind about tech developments. Chapter 9 also looks at accelerated diffusion of innovations, accelerated corporate success, yet shorter cor-porate lifespans. AI, VR, AR, MR, IoT, MA Digital Transformationand much more are explored in Chapter 9, Digital innovation.</p>

<p><bold>Digital marketing excellence Waves of change</bold></p>
<p>Figure 1.3 shows the relentless waves of innovation we have seen through industrialization. These waves of innovation continue to shorten, the fifth wavestill ongoing. The sixth wave, marked by artificial intelligence and digitization across information of things (IoT), robotics and drones is already underway. Further automation of systems, predictive analytics, and data processing will all make an impact. In turn, physical goods and services will likely be digitized. The time to complete tasks could shift from hours to even seconds. At the same time, clean tech could come to the forefront. At the heart of each technological innovation is solving complex problems, and climate concerns are becoming increasingly pressing. Lower costs in solar PV and wind are also predicating efficiency advantages (Neufeld 2021).</p>

<fig fig-type="figure" id="F1.3" position="float">
<label>FIGURE 1.3</label>
<caption>The history of innovation cycle</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="Fig.3.tif"/>
<p>Source: The Visual Capitalist – adapted from Eddison Institute <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:"href="https://www.visualcapitalist.com/the-history-of-innovation-cycles./">https://www.visualcapitalist.com/the-history-of-innovation-cycles./"</ext-link></p>
</fig>

<fig fig-type="figure" id="F1.4" position="float">
<label>FIGURE 1.4</label>
<caption>Average number of digital devices we use today</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="Fig.4.tif"/>
<p>Source: Deloitte (2020)</p>
</fig>

<p><bold>The connected world</bold></p>
<p>Of the eight billion people on the planet around 60% are connected to the Internet (Datare- portal 2021). There is still potential for growth since many countries still do not have a proper digital infrastructure. This is digital poverty and it restricts the economic growth of these coun-tries and the businesses within it. Plus digital exclusion happens in all countries since some people do not have the wealth or skills to access the web.</p>

<p>Meanwhile the number of connected devices, partly because of the Internet of Things (IoT,) reached 25 billion globally in 2021 (Gartner). So in addition to desktops, tablets, smartphones and smart watches, anything can connect with anything including cars, bikes, cards, golf clubs and tennis rackets as long as they have a sensor/camera, plus with a chip plus wireless connection they can connect to other devices. See Chapter 9 for more on IoT. The average number of smart devices per person is also growing (Figure 1.4).</p>

<p>It is interesting to note that the amount of data sharing has increased. Although we know our data is precious and should be managed very carefully, we seem to be happy to share (or give away) our personal data increasingly over the last five years (Deloitte 2020, discussed further in Chapter 2).</p>


<p><bold>Disruptive business models</bold></p>
<p>Amidst this radical period of accelerated change, we are witnessing new business models. Chapter 3 explores this in a lot more detail. But for now, consider carefully Tom Goodwin&#x0027;s observation about disruptive business models: &#x201C;Uber, the world&#x0027;s largest taxi company, owns no vehicles. Facebook, the world&#x0027;s most popular media owner, creates no content. Alibaba, the most valuable retailer, has no inventory. And Airbnb, the world&#x0027;s largest accommodation provider, owns no real estate.&#x201D; And this was written way back in 2015. The <italic>Harvard Business Revie</italic><italic>w</italic> more recently revealed ten new truths in a post-COVID world. Top of the list was &#x201C;Know Your Customers&#x0027; Changing Post-Covid Attitudes,&#x201D; which effectively meant new atti- tudinal segments (see Digital marketing insight: changing customer attitudes and segments).</p>

<table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
<label>TABLE 1.1</label>
<caption>A comparison of GDP and market capitalization</caption>
<table frame="box" rules="rows">
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Country/Company</th>
<th>Nominal GDP (country) or market cap (company)</th>
</tr>
</thead>

<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle">United States of America</td>
<td align="left" valign="middle">$21,433 B</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle">China</td>
<td align="left" valign="middle">$14,343 B</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle">Japan</td>
<td align="left" valign="middle">$5,082 B</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle">Germany</td>
<td align="left" valign="middle">$3,861 B</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle">India</td>
<td align="left" valign="middle">$2,869 B</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle">United Kingdom</td>
<td align="left" valign="middle">$2,829 B</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle">France</td>
<td align="left" valign="middle">$2,716 B</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle"><bold>Apple</bold></td>
<td align="left" valign="middle"><bold>$2,125 B</bold></td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle">Italy</td>
<td align="left" valign="middle">$2,004 B</td>
</tr>


<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle"><bold>Microsoft</bold></td>
<td align="left" valign="middle"><bold>$1,942 B</bold></td>
</tr>


<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle"><bold>Saudi Aramco</bold></td>
<td align="left" valign="middle"><bold>$1,888 B</bold></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>

<p><bold>Changing power shifts from government to tech giants?</bold></p>
<p>There is a view from the UN Panel on Digital Co-operation that a major power shift is occur-ring as the size and scale of tech giants is so massive and powerful today, that perhaps inevitably governments/states are receding in importance (Slaughter 2019). We already have currencies (crypto) being created by non-governmental bodies. The major &#x201C;digital &#x2019;&#x2019;platforms or online services sometimes described by the acronym &#x201C;FAMGA&#x201D; dominate the digital world. FAMGA stands for Facebook (who own Instagram and WhatsApp), Amazon, Microsoft (which owns LinkedIn), Google (whose parent group Alphabet&#x2122; owns YouTube and controls the Android mobile phone operating system) and Apple (who control iOS). Apple, Microsoft, Amazon and Google have each reached market capitalizations (valuations) well above $1.5 trillion (Wallach 2021). Private companies have taken over the space race from governments.</p>
<p>Consider the market capitalization of Apple (how much the stock market thinks the com-pany is worth) is estimated at $2.1 trillion (= $2,100 billion), which is larger than the GDP of most countries (96%) in the world, a list that includes Brazil, Canada and Russia. Gross domestic product (GDP) is the total value of all goods and services produced by a country in a year. Saudi Arabia&#x2019;s state-owned corporation Saudi Aramco has a market capitalization of $1. 9trillion = more than double the GDP of its home country, Saudi Arabia. So, although we are comparing different metrics (market cap v GDP), it still demonstrates the size, scale and perhaps influence of the tech giants. Table 1.1 compares the market capitalization of multiple tech giants and compares them with the annual GDP of countries (Lishchuk 2021).</p>
<p><italic>Why does this matter to digital marketers?</italic></p>
<p>These digital platforms have far more power than any previous media owners such as pub-lishers or TV channels. From a practical point of view, the majority of media spend is now online with the majority ofthis divided by what has been called the Facebook-Google duopoly. eMarketer (2019) reports that within the United States and United Kingdom more than 60% ofdigital media spend is now with Facebook and Google.This has led to increased competition on these platforms with auction-based media spend driving advertising higher. Many consider this situation and the limited tax paid by some of these companies anti-competitive, and this has led to the anti-trust investigations in the United States and Europe. Marketers needto develop the specific skills to compete effectively using these platforms. They also need to thinkcreatively about how their brand can engage without these platforms. We explain the organic and paid media options and best practices for these platforms inChapter 7.</p>
<p><bold>Digital marketing insight Customer attitudes and segments</bold></p>
<p>The <italic>Harvard Business Review</italic> (HBR) article "10 Truths about Post Covid Marketing" (Balis 2021) reveals that marketing messages must be personally relevant, aligned to an individual&#x0027;s situation and values as opposed to demographics (italic.e. multiple dimensions that influence buying behaviour). Top of the list, truth no.1, is this:</p>
<p>Old truth: marketing begins with knowing your customer.</p>
<p>New truth: marketing begins with knowing your customer segment. HBR refer to five new post-COVID segments/cohorts of buyers (drawn from the EY Future Consumer Index] with very different attitudes and priorities:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item><bold>Affordability first</bold> (32% of consumers): living within their means and budget, focusing less on brands and more on product functionality</list-item>
<list-item><bold>Health first</bold> (25%): protecting their health and that of their family, choosing products they trust to be safe and minimizing risks in the way that they shop</list-item>
<list-item><bold>Planet first</bold> (16%): trying to minimize their impact on environment and buying brands that reflect their belief</list-item>
<list-item><bold>Society first</bold> (15%): working together for the greater good, buying from organizations they find to be honest and transparent</list-item>
<list-item><bold>Experience first</bold> (12%): living in the moment to make the most of life, often making them open to new products, brands, and experiences</list-item>
</list>
<p>Segmenting customers and defining personas bring deeper insights to inform the full customer journey (which we explore in Chapter 2, Digital Marketing Customers).</p>
<p><bold>Section 1.1 summary</bold></p>
<p>This is a period of unprecedented change in the connected world. We have witnessed disrup-tive models, changing power-shifts from government to tech and observed changing customer attitudes and segments. To compete, marketers must understand the dominant FAMGA plat-forms and use creativity to gain cut-through.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S1.2">
<title>1.2 PURPOSE-DRIVEN MARKETING</title>
<p>We asked the question &#x201C;why digital marketing&#x201D;? The only viable answer to compete is &#x201C;to help customers&#x201D; since happy customers= sales and profits = happy shareholders. Look at Amazon - the most customer-centric company in the world. The next, even bigger question is &#x201C;what isyour mission&#x201D;? Google&#x2019;s mission statement: &#x201C;to organize the world&#x2019;s information and make it universally accessible and useful&#x201D; makes a lot of sense. Your mission is your raison d&#x2019;etre (the reason your organization exists}. &#x201C;This must include how you make the world a better place - how you ultimately help customersand stakeholders. It should also demonstrate someCSR(Corporate Social Responsibility} while giving strategic direction for the organization&#x201D; (Smith 2021}.</p>
<p>Then you have the crunch question: &#x201C;does your mission statement make your staff feel good about coming to work? Are they even aware of the missionstatement?&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>Digital marketing excellence A man on the moon</bold></p>
<p>When John F. Kennedy visited NASA, he met a janitor and asked him what he did. The janitor said: "I&#x0027;m helping to put a man on the moon." A strong mission delivers a greater shared sense of purpose for all staff (Smith 2022).</p>
<p><italic>What is your purpose?</italic></p>
<p>All staff and all stakeholders should feel a sense of purpose from your mission statement.</p>
<p>Your mission statement also helps you later, whenyou develop your strategy and specifically when you choose your positioning (how you want people to perceive you - see Chapter 10). Check that your positioning is something (1} your customers want (2} you candeliver and (3} better than your competitors. A goodmission motivates your staff. It creates a real sense of purpose.</p>
<p>Digital marketing excellence Start with why</p>
<p>A sense of purpose is important, partly because customers like to buy brands that stand for somethingand partly because staff like to work for an organization that stands for something more than just making money. Something deeper. Find your sense of purpose&#x002D;your passion.</p>
<p>“You simply cannot drive sustained performance and high levels of achievement in one’s job and careerwithout being fully engaged and feeling a strong sense of purpose.The common element that often is the spark plug for change and progress is a sense of purpose”(Moore 2017).</p>
<p>World-class companies profit from passion and purpose. These are “Firms of Endearment” that “endear” themselves to customers and communities.</p>
<table frame="box" rules="cols">
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle">In ten years
S&P 500 grew by 122%</td>
<td align="left" valign="middle">Firms of endearment grew by 1000% +</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>Sisodia 2014</p>
<p>"If you don&#x0027;t stand for something you&#x0027;re dead; it&#x0027;s just a question of when" (Sisodia 2014).</p>
<p>Simon Sinek&#x0027;s Golden Circle is a catalyst for change and empahises the importance of &#x0027;purpose&#x0027;.</p>
<p>The Golden Circle theory explains how leaders caninspire cooperation, trust and change in a business based on his research into how the most successful organizations think, act and communicate if they "Start with why," italic.e. they define their purpose.</p>
<p>Sinek explains that " &#x0027;Why&#x0027; is probably the most important message that an organization or individual can agree to communicate as this is what inspires others to action." &#x0027;Why&#x0027; is how you explain your purpose and the reason you exist and behave as you do. Sinek&#x0027;s theory is that successfully communicating that the passion behind the &#x0027;why&#x0027; is a way to communicate with the listener&#x0027;s limbic brain. This is thepart of our anatomy that processes feelings such as trust and loyalty - as well as decision-making. Communicating your &#x0027;why&#x0027; is the basis of astrong value proposition that will differentiate your brand from others.</p>
<fig fig-type="figure" id="F1.5" position="float">
<label>FIGURE 1.5</label>
<caption>Simon Sinek&#x0027;s Golden Circle. Source: Smart Insights (2021; Chaffey 2022)</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="Fig1.5.tif"/>
</fig>
<p><bold>Purpose-driven businesses win</bold></p>
<p>Purpose-driven companies witness higher market share gains and grow three times faster on average than their competitors, all while achieving higher workforce and customer satisfaction.</p.
<p>Today&#x2019;s consumers often identify with a brand&#x2019;s purpose, seeking to connect at a deeper level even as the brand reciprocally aligns with who they are and who they want to be.</p>
<p>It is an organization&#x2019;s soul and identity, providing both a platform to build upon and a mirror to reflect its existence in the world. It articulates why an organization exists, what problems it is here to solve, and who it wants to be to each human it touches through its work . . . businesses are using purpose to create deeper connections with consumers, do more for the communities with which they work, attract and retain talent, and in the process, are achieving greater results and impact.</p>
<p>Deloitte Insight (O&#x2019;Brien et al 2019)</p>
<p><bold>The emergence of stakeholder capitalism and stakeholder marketing</bold></p>
<p>John Elkington introduced the triple bottom line (TBL) of people, planet and profit in 1993. Since then it has gained traction as shown in Figure 1.6. Kofi Annan commissioned the landmark study &#x201C;Who Cares Wins&#x201D; in 2005, which led to environmental, social and governance (ESG), which help responsible investors to integrate ESG factors when choosing where to invest. There are 1,000+ ESG indexes, reflecting investors&#x2019; growing appetite for ESG products. There is also a need to rigorously measure the fulfilment of objectives promised to sustainable investors. Principles for responsible investment (PERI) was launched in 2006 at the New York Stock Exchange (with 1,600 members representing over $70 trillion assets). In 2007 B Corps emerged (they consider social and environmental alongside financial returns). Then Larry Fink, CEO of Blackrock, who oversees $6 trillion of investment, said &#x201C;Purpose is not the sole pursuit of profits but the animating force for achieving them.&#x201D; The Business Roundtable (USA) 181 CEOs signed this new statement of purpose in 2019 &#x201C;Businesses should be run for the benefit of all stakeholders&#x201D; (Note: this rejected the previous dogma: &#x201C;Firms should primarily serve shareholders&#x201D;). This was followed by the chairman of the World Economic Forum, Klaus Schwab, announcing stakeholder capitalism in 2019: &#x201C;We should seize this moment to ensure that stakeholder capitalism remains the new dominant model&#x201D; (Klaus 2019). Although stakeholder capitalism was first launched by Adolf Berle and Gardiner Means in the 1932 management classic, <italic>The Modern Corporation,</italic> we would like to acknowledge the term stakeholder marketing.</p>
<fig fig-type="figure" id="F1.6" position="float">
<label>FIGURE 1.6</label>
<caption>The evolution of stakeholder capitalism.</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="Fig1.6.tif"/>
</fig>
<p><italic>Avoid "purpose wash" and "green wash"</italic></p>
<p>Some coffee companies want to build communities, but don&#x2019;t pay tax.
Some oil companies talk about a sustainable future but still produce fossil fuels and invest millions to lobby against environmental protection laws.</p>
<p>Note: digital activities have a significant impact on energy usage. Be ready for the next wave of green issues emerging from digital usage.</p>
<bold>Digital marketing excellence COVID accelerates purposeful brands and businesses</bold>
<p>Brands are playing an ever more active role in society today, but if many are to thrive over the next five to ten years, " &#x0027;purpose&#x0027; has to be embedded at the very heart of business and culture."</p>
<p>Doing good is good business and social purpose drives sales. In what has been a tough year for consumers because of the Coronavirus pandemic, a brand&#x0027;s purpose has taken centre stage. Consumers are buying from businesses that show empathy and long-term commitment to issues that matter to them. And brands are realizing that authenticity and trust are fundamental in driving these connections with consumers.</p>
<p>"Prior to the pandemic there was this movement towards wanting sustainable, accessible and inclusive products, but this has all accelerated," said MJ DePalma, head of inclusive marketing for Microsoft Advertising.M Baker 2020</p>
<p>Once again, the COVID pandemic has driven a change in attitudes, to the extent that American writer Mark Schaefer created his own manifesto for human-centred marketing (Figure 1.7).</p>
<fig fig-type="figure" id="F1.7" position="float">
<label>FIGURE 1.7</label>
<caption>> A manifesto for human-centred marketing.
Source: Schaefer (2019). Reproduced by kind permission of Mark Schaefer</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="Fig1.7.tif"/>
</fig>
<P><bold>Volvo share safety belt patent with competitors</bold><P>
<p>Some visionary companies like Volvo embraced stakeholder marketing principles back in the 1950s. Volvo gave away the patent for, arguably, its most important invention: the life-saving three-point seat belt, because Volvo felt it was &#x201C;too significant not to share.&#x201D;</p>
<p>Estimates suggest up to 1 million lives have been saved because of the three-point safety belt. Invented in 1959 and eventually installed in all Volvo cars in 1963, Volvo opened up the patent to help any car manufacturer to use it. &#x201C;The invention was so significant, it had more value as a free life-saving tool than something to profit from&#x201D; (England 2013).</p>
<p>Volvo&#x2019;s managing director Alan Dessell is quoted as saying: &#x201C;The decision to release the three-point seat belt patent was visionary and in line with Volvo&#x2019;s guiding principle of safety&#x201D; (Clarke 2013).</p>
<p>Every car manufactured today uses three-point seat belts . . . and it all started with a Volvo PV544 delivered to a dealership in the town of Kristianstad, Sweden (England 2013).</p>
<p><bold>Relentlessly relevant brands</bold>
Today&#x2019;s customers are ruthless at ignoring the tens of thousands of brands that don&#x2019;t interest them. But for their favourites, they welcome with open arms new approaches. These brand favourites continuously focus on loyalty and re-earning that loyalty. They do something other brands don&#x2019;t: they relentlessly pursue new ways to connect with, engage and excite their customers (see Coca-Cola in this chapter). Scott Davis (2020) suggests that they use four factors:</p><p>
(1) customer obsession; (2) ruthless pragmatism (they try new ideas, fail fast, experiment, are always available where ever customers have the need, have great CX and constantly make life easier for theircustomers); (3) pervasive innovation (make emotionalconnections, earn trust and often exist to fulfil a larger purpose); (4) distinctive inspiration (engagewith customers in new and creative ways and find newways to address unmet needs). Did you notice that these excellent companies &#x201C;earn trust and oftenexist to fulfil a larger purpose&#x201D;? Purpose combined with passion is a powerful combination that leads to success. There is a lot more on purpose and passion in the Actions section in Chapter 10 (Digital marketing plan).</p>
<p><bold>Responsible AI</bold></p>
<p>As mentioned at the beginning of this chapter, the pace of technical advances is accelerating, nowhere more so than Artificial Intelligence (AI) as we will see from examples throughout this book and, in particular, Chapter 9, Digital innovation. AI is already adding value to customer experiences, developing new products, setting prices, improving customer communications and much more. As AI continuously and rapidly improves, you need to ask that same question: &#x201C;how does this help my customer?&#x201D; Some of the time it will be all about improving efficiencies and effectiveness, and other times it will be surprisingly creative, like finding new product ideas and creating communications (conversations, headlines, copy, artwork) all potentially personalized and so relevant to each individual customer that it may first seem wonderful</p>.
<p><italic>Can AI be used immorally?</italic></p>
<p>We have already seen the abuse of data by Cambridge Analytica and subsequent illegal ads being used in US election campaigns and the BREXIT campaign in the UK. The debate rolls on regarding data usage. Some businesses have suffered &#x201C;Negative SEO&#x201D; where poor quality backlinks are automatically pointed to their site, although Google has developed filters to try to identify this, moving on to trolls who can track relevant conversations, view profiles and post personalized inflammatory, rude or upsetting statements online to elicit strong emotional responses or to steer the conversation off-topic. Fuelling society with misinformation and disinformation can break down society and perhaps democracy. Trolling can be done by humans or AI-driven chatbots to influence buyers, voters or just attitudes and opinions. This can be organized by &#x201C;hostile states&#x201D; who are fanning extremism as a means to create a terrorist threat within a host country. Could AI-driven bots be ever used to unfairly or immorally win business or change brand attitudes?</p>
<p><italic>The power of AI</italic></p>
<p>Chapter 9 explores the types of AI that help marketers, AI challenges, opportunities and solu-tions in much more detail. We certainly need to be aware of the power of AI and the importance of ethical and responsible use of AI. There is, of course, an argument that Super AI could have the capability to decideto rid humanity of humanity (if it was given a briefto &#x201C;stop world hunger&#x201D; or &#x201C;save the planet&#x201D;). As technology development accelerates, new philosophical, theological and business debates will emerge. It is important to stay abreast of these developments, discussions and decisionsin the future.</p>
<p>One final recommendation is to read Mark O&#x2019;Connell&#x2019;s thought provoking article from 2017 &#x201C;Your animal life is over. Machine life hasbegun.&#x201D;
Meanwhile, here&#x2019;s Professor Klaus Schwab, founder and executive chairman of the World Economic Forum observation &#x201C;There Has Never Been a Time of Greater Promise or Potential Peril&#x201D; (2016).You can read the full quote in Chapter 9. In the interim, here&#x2019;s how Coca Cola are using AI andfresh thinking to engage their customers and learn from them so that they too can use insights-driven marketing to boost their results.</p>
<p><bold>Digital marketing insight Coca-Cola&#x0027;s AI</bold></p>
<p>Coca-Cola markets 500 soft drinks in more than 200 countries with 80,000 employees. Converging big data from social media, mobile apps, cloud computing and e-commerce helps Coca-Cola to "relate to our customers and bolster advocacy. It leverages the data it collects from its customers across the globe" (Jarrell 2021). The 50,000 Coca-Cola Freestyle drink dispensers allow customers to select 200 sparkling and still drinks (plus combine beverages from the entire portfolio) and dispense 14 million beverages every day (Freestyle is a billion-dollar business now).</p>
<p>Of the beverages consumed from Freestyle dispensers, 48% are products that are outside of the conventional top ten. The data gleaned from these self-serving dispensers uncovered valuable insights about customer preferences in different locations and times of the year, which helped to develop a suite of new drinks.</p>
<p>They use machine learning to learn how to read accurately the numbers inside the bottle caps so they can run efficient sales promotions.</p>
<p>"In order to use the mobile app, consumers need to register with their social media account. Coca-Cola uses AI to analyse the social media content of their consumers, gener-ating insights on where, when and how its products are consumed."</p>
<p>Coca-Cola can now "create social media material that is more likely to resonate with its target demographic in various regions across the world thanks to AI image analysis, resulting in a more efficient use of marketing expenditures and, ideally, greater sales margins." Jarrell (2021)</p>
<p><bold>Section 1.2 summary</bold></p>
<p>Purpose-driven businesses are proving that they outperform those that don&#x2019;t have a real purpose or even a mission statement. Stakeholder capitalism is here and now we are declaring it as a time when stakeholder marketing has arrived. Today&#x2019;s brands need to stay relentlessly relevant. Observe the emerging importance of responsible AI.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S1.3">
<title>1.3 INSIGHTS-DRIVEN MARKETING</title>
<p>Although many CEOs want their businesses to be data-driven, it is actually insights from data that create competitive advantage. Hence insights-driven is actually a better term to use, and its use is increasing by commentators; see for example, Forrester 2017. You can explain to her/ him that &#x201C;data isn&#x2019;t the challenge it&#x2019;s creating insights that is the challenge.&#x201D;</p>
<p>Forrester (2017) declared that insights are &#x201C;a competitive differentiator that will make or break your long-term success.&#x201D; They even went so far as to say that a digital strategy could be to: &#x201C;harness digital insights to optimize product and service delivery.&#x201D; We will explain later why we think strategy is more than just insights (see Strategy in Chapter 10), although we do agree that insights can and do create competitive advantage.</p>
<p>Some call it data-centric marketing. Regardless of what you call it, data enables companies to become data-centric and &#x201C;build (or rebuild) their business into one that makes decisions based on metrics, as opposed to the feelings of top executives&#x201D; (Manevich 2020). Others recommend &#x201C;leveraging advanced analytics to support decisioning and reduce risk that can be run against a number of possible scenarios&#x201D; (Kathy Bachmann, Analytic Partners Inc. in an interview with Paul Talbot 2020). You get the idea - making decisions based on data and insights reduces risk and improves the likelihood of success.</p>
<p><bold>Data is the new oil</bold></p>	
<p>On May 6, 2017, the front cover of the <italic>Economist</italic> had an extraordinarily informative message. Something we kind of knew, but perhaps manyof us had not articulated it like this: &#x201C;The world&#x2019;s most valuable resource is no longer oil, but data.&#x201D; There it was. Simple and beautiful in its clarity.  massive statement that affect every person in business - and in particular, in marketing - today. Remember, data is an asset, and justlike any other asset it depreciates over time if it is not maintained (cleaned and stored securely). Assets can become liabilities if unmaintained. A building is an asset but if it is not maintained and it collapses it can killsomeone, plus its owners will be sued. Data is an asset that, if not maintained and held securely, will cause problems with customers anddata institutions.Some estimates suggest that a customer database deteriorates at the rate of 25% each year as people die,change jobs, or move countries.</p>
<fig fig-type="figure" id="F1.8" position="float">
<label>FIGURE 1.8</label>
<caption>Data is the new oil.The <italic>Economist.</italic></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="Fig1.8.tif"/>
</fig>
<p><bold>Building an Insights-Driven Business with The Virtuous Circle Of Data</bold></p>
<p>Ant Bank (China) - collect more data all the tim = more data = better analysis = better insights = better new products = more sales = more customers (an more customer data from same customers) = more data=more insights etc. etc.</p>
<p>Constantly asking questions of their data, they discovered that a disproportionate number of young women with tight jeans break their mobile phone screens . . . so they launched an insurance service for a few cents a week only to ladies with tight jeans. Ithas become yet another successful product from Ant. See more on Ant in Chapter 9.</p>
<p><bold>The virtuous circle of insights-driven marketing</bold></p>
<p>We believe that creating an insights-driven culture and process within a business and, in par-ticular,within marketing is so important that this needs to be a vision enacted in all businesses.
Simply put,</p>
<list list-type="none">
<label>collect more data (all the time)</label>
<list-item>better analysis</list-item>
<list-item>better insights</list-item>
<list-item>better new products and service</list-item>
<list-item>more sales</list-item>
<list-item>more customers*</list-item>
<list-item>more data</list-item>
<list-item>more insights</list-item>
</list>
<p>A change of mindset is needed to create a vision where data is managed as a business asset rather than a by-product of running an option. We have summarized this vision in our virtuous cycle of insights-driven marketing shown in Figure 1.9.</p>
<fig fig-type="figure" id="F1.9" position="float">
<label>FIGURE 1.9</label>
<caption>The Virtuous Circle of Insights-Driven Marketing.</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="Fig1_9.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The vision of insights-driven marketing starts with considering how you can <italic>capture</italic> more and better quality data. For example, in Chapter 5 on campaign planning we explain how it&#x2019;s important to carefully tag your email marketing and social media communications so you can better understand what&#x2019;s effective. You can also add value to data by integrating different data from different customer data sources collected by MarTech, then enriching it where possible through third-party data. Data enrichment tools are increasingly used to add detail to our customer knowledge for B2B data (for example information on product affinity and income) and B2C data (for example, richer profile data for sales intelligence available from tools such as Clearbit, Datanyze and Enrich.io (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.g2.com/categories/sales-intelligence">www.g2.com/categories/sales-intelligence</ext-link></p>
<p>Next, consider you can <italic>Analyse</italic> better since that is of little value unless it is reviewed and acted on to make improvements or address problems. Data that isn&#x2019;t actionable is of little value; it&#x2019;s likely that you have Google Analytics installed on your website, but if it isn&#x2019;t regularly reviewed and acted on this is a huge missed opportunity we have seen in many businesses, particularly smaller businesses. Smart Insights (2015) summarized the pre-requisites of people, process, KPIs and Tools (MarTech) for what they called &#x201C;Actionable Analytics,&#x201D; which are particularly important to improve off-site and on-site marketing communications. From a practical point of view, selecting the right dashboards to summarize year-on-year and month- on-month performance are critical. Using AI to augment standard reports by providing insights that would be difficult for an analyst to identify are important.</p>
<p><italic>Sell</italic> is the final component of the virtuous circle; it&#x2019;s ensuring that insight drives business improvement by using it to improve the customer experience and brand satisfaction. As we&#x2019;ll see, automating &#x201C;always-on&#x201D; communications such as email and web prospect welcome, lead nurture and customer onboarding are important here.</p>
<p><bold>Digital marketing excellence Insights-driven businesses gain competitive advantage</bold></p>
<p>A new kind of company - we call them insights-driven businesses - has formed. These firms use data, analytics and software in closed, continuously optimized loops to differen-tiate and compete. By capturing more and better data and continuously developing and 
implementing insights about what drives their business, they run faster and fleeter than you. Customer insight (CI) pros must help their firms learn to do what insights-driven businesses do.</p>
<p>An Insights-Driven Business systematically harnesses data and applies analytically derived insight to create differentiated experiences and competitive advantage.</p>
<p>Insights-driven businesses create a closed-loop insights process to optimize every customer engagement and every facet of their business. They marry algorithms and expertise to continuously improve outcomes. These firms teach valuable lessons in culture, process, talent, teams and technology. An Insights-Driven Business harnesses and applies data and analytics at every opportunity to differentiate its products and customer experiences.</p>
<p>We forecast that these insights-driven public companies will grow 27% annually, and the start-ups will grow 40% - much faster than the projected global 3.5% GDP growth. Why? Because they harness digital insights to optimize their products, services and operations. McCormick et al (2016)</p>
<p><italic>Data-driven CMOs gain CEO trust (and budgets)</italic>
CEOs have become suspicious of marketers. In fact, we know of some banks that used to refer to their marketing department as &#x201C;the colouring department.&#x201D; We were the people who used to say &#x201C;Half my advertising is wasted . . . but don&#x2019;t know which half.&#x201D; This is an outrageous statement and totally unacceptable for a CEO who lives amidst the white heat of hyper-competition to hear his/her CMO speaking about not knowing which half of budget is wasted.</p>
<p>It is not surprising to see the 2020 Research by the Fournaise Marketing Group reveal that 80% of the CEOs surveyed don&#x2019;t trust their CMOs or are unimpressed by them. &#x201C;This number is a sharp contrast to how CEOs feel about other executives on their team. For instance, only 10% of those CEOs feel the same way about their CFOs and CIOs&#x201D; (Manevich 2020).</p>
</p>Manevich continues:</p>
,p>Unlike a CFO, a non-technology-minded CMO is not able to justify their spending because they don&#x2019;t have the infrastructure set up to track and report on their mar-keting efforts from the start. Whereas a marketing technologist or a CMO with a digital background would build such an infrastructure and be able to communicate, structure and report on the KPIs achieved by their team.</p>
</p>So data-driven, or insights-driven, we marketers must be able to base decisions and requests for budgets on hard evidence, data, insights, call it what you will.</p>
<fig fig-type="figure" id="F1.10" position="float">
<label>FIGURE 1.10</label>
<caption> Requirements for actionable analytics.
Source: Smart Insights (2015)</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="Fig1_10.tif"/>
</fig>
<p><bold>Do marketers have the skills?</bold></p>
<p>Your marketing audit (which you carry out as part of your Situation Analysis in your plan, see Chapter 10) should reveal what skills you have and what skills you need to develop or buy in.
Lori Niles (2020), a LinkedIn Learning Strategist, suggests that one third of your current skill will not be required by 2023. This sounds a bit shocking but certainly does bring to mind Alvin Toffler&#x2019;s words: winners will be &#x201C;those that can learn, unlearn and relearn.&#x201D;</p>
<p><bold>Section 1.3 summary</bold></p>
<p>Data is the new oil. A data-driven business is now upgraded to an insights-driven business. After all, that&#x2019;s why we crunch data - to find insights from the data. The Virtuous Circle of Data offers great potential to all businesses. We are aware of the importance of an Insights-Driven Business benefitand resource shortage.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S1.3">
<title>1.4 DIGITAL MARKETING DEFINITIONS AND ESSENTIAL CONCEPTS</title>
<p>As digital marketing has changed the way we do business and marketing, many new labels have been used to highlight these new opportunities. Not all labels are perhaps useful, for us &#x201C;Big Data&#x201D; was &#x201C;Big Hype&#x201D; from MarTech vendors, for example, but new marketing concepts such as inbound and lifecycle marketing are useful to help your colleagues or clients understand potential improvements to communications</p>.
<p><bold>Digital marketing and e-commerce definitions</bold></p>
<p>Since there are many terms or jargon used in digital marketing today let us briefly define and clarify a few terms that can cause some confusion and somethat highlight trends such as sub-scription and conversational commerce. We highlight new terms we introduce in bold that are listed in the Glossary</p>.
<p>Marketing (online and offline) has been usefully defined as the management discipline responsible fo &#x201C;identifying, anticipating and satisfying customer requirements profitably.&#x201D; This Chartered Institute of Marketing (CIM) definition looks not only at identifying customer needs but also satisfying them (short-term) and anticipating them in the future (long-term retention). We would also consider changing &#x201C;profitably&#x201D; for &#x201C;efficiently&#x201D; in any definition to allow for not- for-profit organizations.</p>
<p>Digital marketing has the same responsibilities of identifying, anticipating and satisfying customer requirements efficiently - through the use of digital (or online) tools and techniques. Soon &#x201C;Digital Marketing&#x201D; will be just considered as a fundamental part of marketing. Integrating digital (or online) with offline marketing is essential, so ensure you explain how digital marketing activities are integrated with other communications and aligned to marketing goals.</p>
<p>E-commerce refers to all electronically mediated information exchanges between an organi-zation and its external stakeholders. It often refers to purchase transactions only italic.e. online sales where a commercial transaction takes place (this includes integrated processes for showing stock availability (or service availability), placing orders, order acknowledgement, payment, data security, logistics, accounting and finance).</p>
<p>Subscription commerce is increasing in importance as explained in Chapter 3. This is defined as a business model that allows customers to subscribe to products or services they need on a recurring basis. A benefit is that this model can increase your customer&#x2019;s lifetime value significantly.</p>
<p>Conversational commerce Although similar to conversational marketing, conversational commerce goes a step further than finding information and booking appointments; it completes the sale. See Chapter 9 formore detail.</p>
<p>Digital business (E-business) is broader than e-commerce referring to all electronically mediated information exchanges supporting the range of business processes, both within an organization and with external stakeholders and/or ecosystems. This effectively can include all digital business processes, such as sales, customer service, operations, finance, procurement, logistics and fulfilment, seamlessly integrated and automated, where possible. Since the quality of these activities will ultimately affect customer&#x2019;s and stakeholder&#x2019;s experience and perception of a brand, marketers are now more closelyinvolved with these activities than in the pre-digital age. For example, social listening, which we explore in Chapter 6, reviews social media to identify improvements to product and process.</p>
<p><bold>Intermediary and markets definitions</bold></p>
<p>Intermediaries, distribution channels and influencers all need to be managed carefully. Choos-ing which channel and channel partners to work with is part of strategy (see Chapter 10 section on Strategy). Knowing which channels work best, both now and in the future, is essential, whether dot com brands like Nike and Apple (sell directly via web and stores) or the direct subscription model like the Dollar Shave Company or vertical marketplaces like Airbnb or horizontal marketplaces like eBay and Amazon.</p>
<p><italic>Intermediaries</italic></p>
<p>There are a variety of channels or routes to market (or marketplaces). Some involve intermediaries like retailers. Other don&#x2019;t, as they sell direct. Some others again do both e.g. brands like Nike have traditionally sold through retail stores. Plus, they sell now sell directly to consumers online using what is now called the direct to consumer (D2C or DTC) model via their own site or via horizontal marketplaces like Amazon. Some markets squeeze out the middleman (e.g. holiday markets and travel agents), while others are introducing a middleman e.g. &#x201C;Go Compare,&#x201D; a vertical website for buying insurance. In this more complex trading environment new intermediaries have developed to support brands in different sectors. For example, Young Foodies (Figure 1.11) is an intermediary that supports challenger food and drink brands across all aspects of digital business.</p>
<fig fig-type="figure" id="F1.11" position="float">
<label>FIGURE 1.11</label>
<caption>Young Foodies. An intermediary to support FMCG Brands</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="Fig1_11.tif"/>
</fig>
<p><italic>Horizontal marketplaces</italic></p>
<p>These sell a wide variety of categories e.g. Amazon, eBay, Etsy or Storefront.com and aggregate a wide variety of buyers and sellers. Note: some horizontals start as verticals e.g. eBay started in the collectibles marketplace.</p>
<p><italic>Vertical marketplaces</italic></p>
<p>These sell a variety of goods and services within a vertical (or specific sector) like Airbnb (accommodation). Sometimes called &#x201C;curated marketplaces&#x201D; as they select (curate) and present a collection from many vetted sources e.g. Airbnb or justeat.</p>
<p><bold>Hyperlocal marketplaces</bold></p>
<p>These deliver within a limited area or region often in the shortest time possible.</p>
<p><bold> Cloud marketplaces</bold></p>
<p>Here customers/get access to software apps and services that integrate with the cloud provider e.g. Salesforce&#x2019;s App Exchange, Oracle&#x2019;s Cloud Marketplace and Microsoft&#x2019;s Azure.</p>
<p><italic>Ecosystems</italic></p>
<p>Many SaaS (software as a service) companies like Salesforce or Microsoft have created ecosys-tems where app builders, integrators, consultants, resellersand many more parties collectively create a massive ecosystem. Members interact and innovate with other members ultimately to help clients. See Chapter 9 for more.</p>
<p><italic>Aggregators</italic></p>
<p>A site featuring a range of product or service listings from suppliers; for example, a price comparison intermediary. Prices are usually updated by suppliers using XML feeds. Google Product Search is an example of an aggregator</p>.
<p><italic>Affiliates</italic></p>
<p>Introduce customers to larger brands and earn a commission for doing so. Affiliates can be large players themselves. Look at any airline website and you&#x2019;ll see both hotels and car hire are on offer also. Here the airline is an affiliate partner to the car hire and/or hotel company.</p>
<p><italic>Publishers or media sites</italic></p>
<p>Review sites, comparison sites and media sites. Review sites, like trust pilot, feefoo and reevoo are a key part of the buying process for many customers. A new middleman with more influence advertising. This can also include niche media sites and even podcasts.</p>
<p><italic>Disintermediation</italic></p>
<p>Direct to customer (DTC) includes &#x201C;single item&#x201D; retailing e.g. casper.com mattresses or subscription retailing e.g. dollarshaveclub.com - this is dis-intermediaton italic.e. excluding the middle man and selling directly to the customer. Other DTC include dot.com brands e.g. Nike.com and Apple.com that sell via their website (plus they can have offline (1) dedicated stores and
(2)other retail stores).</p>
<p><bold>Influencer marketing definitions</bold><p>
<p>Influencer marketing is big business - both for the brands and the influencers. The brands get exposure and affection when high profile celebrities wear their brands, use their brands, talk about their brands or sometimes just even are associated with their brands by being a brand ambassador.</p>
<p>We discuss different types of influencers more and how to manage influencer marketing as part of influencer relationship management (IRM) as part of content marketing in Chapter 4.</p>
<p><italic>Influencer categories</italic></p>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>Nano influencers (under 5000 followers)</list-item>
<list-item>Micro and niche influencers (5000-99,999 followers)</list-item>
<list-item>Mid-tier influencers (100,000-999,999 followers)</list-item>
<list-item>Top-tier influencers (1m+ followers) with a global presence</list-item>
<list-item>Authoritative influencers (expert representation of an industry body, journalist, editor etc.)</list-item>
</list>
</p>

<fig fig-type="figure" id="F1.12" position="float">
<label>FIGURE 1.12</label>
<caption>Lil Miquela <ext-link ext-link-type="www.instagram.com/lilmiquela">www.instagram.com/lilmiquela</ext-ref></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="Fig1_12.tif"/>
</fig>

<p><italic>AI influencers</italic></p>
<p>Then there are influential avatars that are AI driven who gain a following and become influ-encers like Lil Miquela on Instagram. Lil is a self-declared robot, and, as well as having 3 m followers on Instagram, she has previously launched her own perfume, song and clothes. Lil also has a conscience and caresabout BLM. Given that an influencer can earn $3,000-$5,000 per tweet (for each 500,000 followers), Lil can earn $18,000-$30,000 per tweet when referring to or wearing a particular brand. That&#x2019;s between$6.6m and $11m if Lil did one tweet on behalf of a brand every day. See PRSmith.org/blog.</p>
<p>Remember many influencers are better than others at building brand awareness while others are able tohelp convert sales. If sales, then the influencers are given a unique trackable link to include in theircontent, or discount codes make it easy for brands to measure sales and conversions.</p>
<p>Other influencers like the beautiful Shudu (the world&#x2019;s first digital supermodel) are the brainchild of a young British fashion photographer who self-taught himself 3D modelling via YouTube videos. Like other models, Shudu influences people. Unlike other models, Shudu is an avatar created by Cameron-James Wilson (see Chapter 2 and prsmith.org/blog for more).</p>
<p>Incidentally, some influencers&#x2019; posts havea &#x201C;knock-on&#x201D; or &#x201C;halo effect&#x201D; when the post is then extended into other channels. For example, creative influencer Rich McCor, known as PaperBoyo on Instagram, posted an image for Lego that was so successful it was then shared by Instagram&#x2019;s own profile and has since made it onto lists and articles on the best Instagram posts. PaperBoyo has shown and talked about this image (seeFigure 1.13) at conferences.</p>

<fig fig-type="figure" id="F1.13" position="float">
<label>FIGURE 1.13</label>
<caption>PaperBoyo&#x0027;s famous Lego image.</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="Fig1_13.tif"/>
</fig>
<p><bold>Essential digital marketing concepts</bold></p>
<p>In this section we describe different labels thathave been created to describe the process of digital marketing, italic.e. how the different media channels such as search, social media and email marketin work together to achieve the goals of customer acquisition and retention. This can be confusing for newcomers to digital marketing or non-specialists, since,as we will see, there is a big overlap between these, so it depends who you are speaking to. . . . Plus,these terms have evolved through time. First we had permission marketing in the late 1990s, then inboundmarketing and lifecycle marketing in the 2010s,whilecontent marketing and marketing automation have beenpossible for a long time to support these processes.We start with customer lifecycle marketing since we think it is the best way to unify these concepts andit applies equally to B2C and B2B marketing. Plus, it involves specific activities that can beused to refine your approach.</p>
<p><italic>Customer lifecycle marketing</italic></p>
<p>Customer lifecycle marketing is an essential way of thinking for marketers. It summarizes a planned approach to scheduling and optimizing continuous always-on marketing activities that support customer acquisition and retention. These activities aim to maximize visibility and persuasion through the customer lifecycle.</p>
<p>Key &#x201C;always-on&#x201D; activities include paid and natural search marketing to increase visibility as visitors search for products, information orentertainment; social media and influence marketing to encourage recommendations. Once visitors are aware of a brand, their interest can be nurtured by marketing automation techniques to feature persuasive content marketing including email marketing, SMS messaging or push notification plus on-site personalization and off- site re-targeting ads.</p>
<p>We like the Smart Insights RACE marketing planning framework developed by Dave Chaffey (Smart Insights, 2010) because it goes further than attention/awareness, interest, desire and action (purchase) (AIDA)since the relationship is only really beginning (notending) when you make that first sale. You can see from the following graphic the array of tactical tools and channels that can be used across the customer lifecyle. It&#x2019;s a modern version of the marketing funnel showing the general sequence of activities in the customer buying process.</p>

<fig fig-type="figure" id="F1.14" position="float">
<label>FIGURE 1.14</label>
<caption>Customer lifecycle marketing. Retail sector example. Source: Smart Insights (2017)</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="Fig1_14.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>customers and fans with brands throughout the customer lifecycle:</p>
<p>Step 1: Reach - Build awareness of a brand, its products and services on other sites and in offline media and build traffic by driving visits to web and social media pres-ences.</p>
<p>Step 2: Act - Engage audience with brand on its website or other online presence to encourage them tointeract with a company or other customers. In many sectors, the aim of the Act stage is lead generation, italic.e. to gain permission to market to a prospect using email, SMS or mobile app notifications.</p>
<p>Step 3: Convert - Achieve conversion to generate sales on web presences and offline. </p><p>Step 4: Engage - Build customer relationships through time toachieve retention goals.</p>
<p>Although RACE is sometimes thought of as a digital marketing planning framework, it&#x2019;s designed to support multichannel (or omnichannel) marketing planning. That is, customer communications and product distribution are supported by a combination of digital and traditional channels at different points in the buying cycle or &#x201C;path to purchase.&#x201D; With the vast number of mobile and IoT touchpoints, some commentators use the term <italic>omnichannel marketing,</italic> particularly in retail.</p>
<p>Digital channels always work best when they are integrated with other channels so, where appropriate, digital channels should be combined with the traditional offline media and channels. The most important aspects of integration are, first, using traditional media to raise awareness of the value of the online presences at the reach and act stages and, second, at the convert and engage steps where customers will often still prefer to interact with customer representatives, and this will typically increase conversion rates, average order value and lifetime value.</p>
<p>Through the engage customer communications activities, RACE also emphasizes the need to manage customer retention from online customer onboarding to loyalty in a structured way. It&#x2019;s the reason why American car salesmen and women were trained to sell ten cars to one individual. What does that mean? It means that each customer will probably buy at least 10 cars over the next 20-30 years. Hence, if you keep the customer happy, keep them engaged and rewarded, italic.e. keep the relationship going, it is likely that you will make many more sales during the life of that one customer. If an average price of a car is $30k then that customer is worth $300k over the next 20-30 years. Isn&#x2019;t it worth keeping in touch, understanding their changing needs, being relevant and helpful all the time?</p>
<p>The previous figure gives an example of the sequence of lifecycle marketing activities that occur through time in the retail sector. B2B examples of RACE created by Smart Insights (2017) show how these visualizations can be used to perform a gap analysis between activities you should be working on or could be. To provide more structure for selecting investments in lifecycle marketing when creating digital marketing plans, Smart Insights (2010) created 20 defined activities to support the marketing goals of each part of RACE. These activities are summarized in Figure 1.14. There is also a plan component of RACE that includes (1) situation and performance analysis; (2) objective and vision setting; (3) strategy development and governance; (4) segmentation and targeting; and (5) brand value proposition development. This summary is complex, but we present it since has proved popular in giving a visual checklist to assess which digital marketing tactics you need to deploy andwhich you need to learn about for career development. We cover all of these techniques in more detail inlater chapters.</p> 


<fig fig-type="figure" id="F1.15" position="float">
<label>FIGURE 1.15</label>
<caption>The RACE omnichannel marketing planning framework summarizing aims, activities and measures.</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="Fig1_15.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>We also like Infusionsoft&#x2019;s lifetime model,which is interesting because of its simplicity and emphasis on the ongoing marketing drive that occurs after the first sale: Attract - Sell
-Wow!</p>
<p><bold>Inbound marketing</bold></p>
<p>Inbound marketing is a similar concept to lifecycle marketing. However, it relates mainly to customer acquisition and lead generation whereas lifecycle marketing also covers retention marketing. It describes a buying process where the consumer is proactive in seeking out infor-mation about products to suit their needs, whereas &#x201C;outbound marketing&#x201D; is pushing messages out via ads and emails.</p>
<p>Traditional media are predominantly push media where the marketing message is broad-cast from company to customer and other stakeholders. During this process, there is limited interaction with the customer, although interaction is encouraged in some cases, such as the direct-response advert or mail-order campaign.</p>
<p>In digital media it is often the customer who initiates contact with a brand and who is seeking information or an experience through visiting a website or company outpost. In other words, it is a pull mechanism where it is particularly important to have good visibility in search engines when customers are entering search terms relevant to a company&#x2019;s products or services. Amongst marketing professionalsthis powerful new approach to marketing is now commonly known as inbound marketing (Halligan and Shaw, 2009).</p>
<p>Inbound marketing is powerful since it is targetswhen they are showing the highest intent, italic.e. they are actively searching for information or products. It&#x2019;s also lower since it&#x2019;s mainlybased on earned and owned media such as content marketing, organic search, social media and influencer marketing, so advertising wastage is reduced. Contentand search marketing can be used to target prospectswith a defined need - they are proactive and self-selecting. But this is a weakness since marketers may have less control than in traditional communicationswhere the message is pushed out to a defined audience and can help generate awareness and demand. Paid search and social media may still be used for techniques such as demand generation for account-based marketing (B2B) and retargeting (B2C and B2B).</p>
<p><bold>Permission marketing</bold></p>
<p>Permission marketing is a key component of lifecycle and inbound marketing. It was intro-duced by Seth Godin in his now classic <italic>Permission Marketing</italic> (Godin 1999) - where essentially marketers seek customer consent - or permission - to email or phone or contact customers. It was written way in advance of GDPR and demonstrates how best practice integrates best ethics and best privacy regs in marketing today.</p>
<p>Success in today&#x2019;s permission marketing requires exceptional, compelling content. To emphasize the importance of content marketing to gaining permission, encouraging sharing and ongoing engagement through websites and social media, the concepts of content marketing and content strategy have developed to describe best practice approaches. By content we refer to the combination of static content forming web pages but also dynamic rich media content that encourages interaction. Videos, podcasts, user-generated content and interactive product selectors should also be considered as content which should be refined to engage site visitors.</p>
<p>You can see the challenge that content strategy presents since there are so many different types of content delivered in different forms to different places on different access platforms, yet it is increasingly important to engage customers in social media. These elements of content marketing need to be planned and managed:</p>
<p><bold>POEM - paid, owned and earned media</bold></p>
<p>Marketing has always involved paid, owned and earned media, but digital marketing has changed the dynamic to give many more options within each, so it&#x2019;s a useful way to simplify the discussion of media spend.</p>
<p>Paid media is what it says on the tin - advertising that includes paid search, display and affiliate marketing. Owned media includes your own website, blogs, social media pages and apps. Earned includes word-of-mouth, discussions, comments, shares, likes, editorial and influencer outreach.</p>
<p><italic>Digital marketing media channels</italic></p>
<p>POEM has a weakness in that it doesn&#x2019;t describe the main channels that people working in marketing invest their time and money in. In the first edition of this book we summarized six main digital media channels. These correspond to the Medium in Google Analytics Acquisition reports used to assess different sources of traffic or referrers to the websiteas explained in Chapter 5.</p>
<p>These six channels remain valid, but there are now new techniques such as programmatic and native advertising which are available, so in this edition we present Figure 1.17 to review the digital media options, which breaks out the six media channels into typical paid, owned and earned techniques. For example,both search and social media marketing include organic and paid options. We will explain the options, typical importance and best practices for these further in Chapter 7.</p>

<fig fig-type="figure" id="F1.16" position="float">
<label>FIGURE 1.16</label>
<caption>The difference between paid, owned and earned media.Source: Smart Insights (2012)</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="Fig1_16.tif"/>
</fig>

<fig fig-type="figure" id="F1.17" position="float">
<label>FIGURE 1.17</label>
<caption>The six key digital media channels and someof the most common paid, owned and earned techniqueswithin them.</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="Fig1_17.tif"/>
</fig>

<p><bold>Content marketing including TOFU, MOFU AND BOFU</bold></p>
<p>We see content marketing as the glue that holds a lot of digital marketing tactics together. Content marketing is the fuel for all your core digital marketing activities like search, social media,email and landing page marketing. We even have types of content - some suited for TOFU (top of funnel), MOFU and BOFU, which we explain in Chapter 4 on content marketing.</p>
<p>&#x201C;Content Is King,&#x201D; and relevant content, in particular, is even more powerful as it can create competitive advantage. Use your visitor/customer data to identify which stage of the buying process a visitor/customer is at and then only serve highly relevant content, just when they need it and where they need it.</p>
<p>Content marketing unifies all of your digital marketing communications to support cus-tomer acquisition, retention and growth goals. A coherent content marketing plan will reduce the need for separate plans for individual digital marketing activities. This naturally creates more powerful integrated campaign plans (Chapter 5)</p>.
<p>Content is key to igniting customer engagement and generating demand via targeted, rel-evant, discoverable and optimized content that gives you and your business the higher level of visibility and authority. Plus, now we know it is important to create content clusters (helps your Google ranking).</p>
<p>Content marketing is not a panacea. No tactic is. It has to be high quality, authoritative, discoverable/accessible, digestible (in a variety of formats). There is a massive amount of content competing for your customer&#x0027;s attention. This comes from attention seeking content beyond your own sector or market. Amidst all of this we have &#x201C;content shock&#x201D; - a moment when your content topic becomes swamped with inferior content from elsewhere and where engagement levels start to fall.</p>
<p><bold>Conversational marketing</bold></p>
<p>Conversational marketing is a broad concept describing different forms of direct digitally mediated communications that has gained traction over the last few years. It covers digital dialogue between a brand and its prospects and customers as part of the customer lifecycle.</p>
<p>Gartner has described it as &#x201C;Conversational marketing technologies enable interactions between companies and customers that mimic human dialogue and do so at scale.&#x201D;</p>
<p>It is defined by IBM (2020) as &#x201C;a method that engages consumers in dialogue-driven, personalized experiences at a one-to-one level, enabling brands to listen and gain unique customer insights while also providing value to the user.&#x201D;</p>
<p>Its importance is suggested by the many channels that are available to facilitate conver-sational marketing. Figure 1.18 summarizes the online messaging techniques for interacting directly with audiences available to businesses. Traditional direct mail can also be used to com-plement these communications. Interaction formats used to deliver communications to indi-viduals are shown in the inner circle. The outer circle shows the many different digital devices that we can use to deliver communications, giving a choice to audiences.</p>

<fig fig-type="figure" id="F1.18" position="float">
<label>FIGURE 1.18</label>
<caption>Digital communications options to support relationship development with online audiences using direct messaging.</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="Fig1_18.tif"/>
</fig>

<p>Although many have proclaimed the &#x201C;death of email&#x201D; over the years, it is still a key digital channel and important in supporting conversational marketing, both through automated, personalized lifecycle email and in delivering customer service. Considering email, Radicati Group (2020) forecast that the total number of business and consumer emails sent each day will grow from 306 billion in 2020 to over 361 billion in 2024. They note that email is still the most pervasive form of electronic communication for both business and consumer users, so it is a key technique alongside mobile text and push notifications and emerging formats. On average, a consumer receives approximately 75 messages per day, so to gain &#x201C;cut-through within the crowded inbox&#x201D; requires both creativity and targeting to deliver a relevant message. Other forms of personal messaging are increasing in importance as catalogued by Datareportal (2021) who reported that globally, three mobile messenger apps (WhatsApp, Facebook Messenger and Weixin/WeChat) had more than one billion monthly active users, and a further three (QQ, Telegram and Snapchat) had more than <sup><italic>x</sup>h<sup></italic></sup> billion monthly users. These may not all offer the sophisticated targeting options of email marketing, but offer the potential to improve customer loyalty by interacting directly with individuals alongside push notifications in mobile apps and SMS text marketing. They&#x2019;re particularly relevant for audiences that don&#x2019;t use email marketing.</p> 
<p>This increase in digital messaging highlights why a lifecycle customer relationship manage-ment strategy informed by data about customers is important to gain audience engagement through more personalized messages that offer greater value than competitor messages, which are less relevant. This chapter details the data-driven analysis and personalization techniques available to the marketer, showing through examples how they can be applied to B2B and B2C markets using marketing automation.</p>
<p>For many businesses, engaging in these types of conversations with clients to gain actionable insight requires scalable technologies such as chatbots or other digital solutions. These tools can be thought of as a new set of ears for marketers and may be embedded in virtually any place you connect with consumers, whether that&#x0027;s on your website, mobile app or even interactive advertisements.</p>
<p>And of course, it also applies to B2B and not just B2C. Imagine driving physical traffic to your store or online traffic to your store. The customer arrives but can&#x0027;t find the special offer that attracted them in the first place. &#x201C;Help!&#x201D; they shout, but no one hears them. Now they are getting angry as you are wasting their time. You invited them into your store or website, but they can&#x2019;t find the special offer. Or simple announcement that you made. This is where even a basic chatbot can at least greet you, ask how they can help you and then try to find a suitable answer for you depending on what trigger words you used. The bot can either then present the information you need or book you an appointment with an expert consultant or even a salesperson by giving access to various diaries so the potential customer can book an appointment. Alternatively, the conversation can be escalated to a supervisor if the visitor wants this.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, we have basic chatbots that help customers at a basic level. Then we have more sophisticated chatbots that can have an open dialogue with you such as Lil Miquela.</p>
<p>Conversational AI, as some call it, uses a combination of rules and machine learning. These chatbots use natural language processing to converse with customers in a &#x201C;natural way.&#x201D; Depending on the customer data, the chat can be personalized according to the chat and also according to the data you have in the customer file. So this can be &#x201C;personalized at scale&#x201D; so that a highly relevant, helpful and personalized experience can be delivered at scale. Simple rules-based chatbots such as those from Drift, Intercom and the HubSpot example shown in Figure 2.1 can also collect insight on customer preferences based on the options selected; so can feedback into the Virtuous Circle of Insight-Driven Marketing. It can also collect traditional feedback and surveys in a friendly and time saving way. See how to &#x201C;Develop your own chatbot&#x201D; inthe Chapter 9 appendix.</p>
<p><bold>Marketing automation</bold></p>
<p>Marketing automation (MA) is all about automated communications (whether an email, a message, a pop-up page, a dynamic page swap showing more relevant material to a particular visitor, or a phone call from a sales rep - all triggered by click behaviour (digital body language) of a visitor (Smith 2020)). Automation is particularly useful for supporting the act, convert and engage customer lifecycle activities shown in Figure 1.14.</p>
<p>Many processes can now be automated in very sophisticated ways. MA&#x2019;s primary goal is to help customers and ultimately acquire customers. MA can improve campaign results, as it generates automatic tailored communications triggered by click behaviour (digital body 1 anguage) and profiles. Figure 1.19 shows a simple B2B example of an email nurture sequence that uses the &#x201C;Rule of Six&#x201D; repeated communication sequence to help engage and convince.</p>

<fig fig-type="figure" id="F1.19" position="float">
<label>FIGURE 1.19</label>
<caption>Digital marketing excellence A simple sample marketing automation system</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="Fig1_19.tif"/>
</fig>

<p>Traditionally, automation is rules-based, but it offers potential to be supported by AI. Mar- Tech vendors have highlighted this by their AI automation sub-brands Einstein (from Sales- force) and Watson (from IBM).</p>
<p>Consider a rules-based example: someone who bounces off the first page (exits) might get a minus score; someone who stays five minutes looking at product pages gets a higher score, and someone else who looks at product pages, leaves the site and later comes back and watches the product video and moves to the shopping basket (but doesn&#x2019;t buy) gets an even higher score. These scores and rules allow the system to automatically respond with tailored relevant messages offering more information or help required via the visitor&#x2019;s preferred channel whether a dynamic web page, a pop-up message, an email, a text or even a request to a rep to phone the prospect. This assumes that the visitor has clearly opted-in and given their data (say, name, email and phone number).</p>
<p>Marketing automation systems help organizations automatically engage with their pros-pects and customers at the right time, with the right content, via the right channel.</p>
<p>A screen grab of an intriguing video clip with attention-grabbing headline is posted across several platforms as part of the continuous inbound marketing campaign. This generates inbound traffic with just one click. Those who watch the video are asked, at the end, if they&#x0027;d like alerts regarding similar videos and reports. A percentage of visitors do so.</p>
<list list-type="none">
<list-item>Step 1: visitor registers name, email and industry.</list-item>
<list-item>Step 2: email them an invitation to download a free report.</list-item>
<list-item>Step 3: send a thank you to the people who visited the site and downloaded the report.</list-item>
<list-item>. Step 4: send them a case study from their industry.</list-item>
<list-item>Step 5: prospects who click on the case study get a "lead score" or "grade" (depending on their click behaviour/digital body language and/or other information collected). </list-item>
<list-item>Step 6: sales rep gets an auto-alert regarding high grade prospects that deserve a follow up.</list-item>
</list>
<p>The steps required to set up a marketing automation programme:</p>
<list list-type="number">
<list-item>Clearly define the stages of a sale (and after sale)
e.g. visitor/prospect - lead - enquiry - customer - advocate.
</list-item>
<list-item>Define and score digital behaviour required for each
stage of a sale, e.g. opening a particular email; visiting a particular page(s); downloading a white paper.
</list-item>
<list-item>Clarify what behaviour/score triggers what response.</list-item>
<list-item>Agree next auto steps for customers who respond ("responders" and "non-responders").</list-item>
</list>
<p>Once this detailed process is rigorously completed, an MA programme can:</p>
<list list-type="none">
<list-item>Integrate social media, direct mail/email, telemarketing and more</list-item>
<list-item>Continually serve tailored and highly relevant web landing pages to different visitors</list-item>
<list-item>Continually respond via dynamic web pages, dynamic emails, pop up messages</list-item>
<list-item>Alert sales or customer service people to call customers</list-item>
</list>
<p>All this without needing assistance from the IT team. You can also set up A/B tests as part of this process to see which pages/offers/photos convert better. The original book on digital body language was written by Steven Woods (co-founder of Eloqua) back in 2009.</p>
<p>(Taken from Smith, PR SOSTAC&#x00AE; Guide to your Perfect Digital Marketing Plan.)</p>
<p><bold>Digital transformation</bold></p>
<p>In the early days of the Internet we recall some &#x201C;snake oil salesmen&#x201D; advising that Internet marketing, as it was then known, was a cheap, quick and easy way to grow a business. Thirty years later we know that, while lifecycle and inbound marketing have many benefits, most would agree they are not simple. The proliferation of digital platforms, channels and devices and constant innovation giving consumers and businesses more choice mean that many businesses have failed to adapt to take advantage of digital marketing. Digital disruption from new dot-com challenger brands, of which Amazon was one of the first, has meant that many existing businesses have lost market share to their more agile online competitors and startups.</p>
</p>In response to these challenges many businesses have started digital transformation pro-grammes. TheSalesforce definition of digital transformation highlights the importance of inte-gration of digital activities across functions and putting customers at the heart of transformation:</p>
<p>Digital transformation is the process of using digital technologies to create new - or modify existing - business processes, culture, and customer experiences to meet changing business and market requirements. This reimagining of business in the digital ageis digital transformation.</p>
<p>It transcends traditional roles like sales, marketing, and customer service. Instead, digital transformation begins and ends with how you think about, and engage with, customers.
Research by Smart Insights (Chaffey 2016) investigated the challenges of managing digital marketing:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>Planning. Nearly half (48%) of businesses surveyed do not have a defined digital plan or strategy although they are active in digital marketing, while more than half (63%) also don&#x2019;t have a clearly-defined integrated marketing communications strategy to align against.</list-item>
<list-item>Organizational capabilities. Many businesses either already have introduced (27%) or were planning to introduce (35%) a digital transformation programme, although a substantial proportion (25%) of businesses don&#x0027;t think it&#x0027;s relevant for them.</list-item>
<list-item>Integration of digital channels into marketing. The survey also asked respondents to rate the maturity of their digital marketing across the customer lifecycle on a five-point scale. The majority of businesses were in categories one to five. For example, for convert, achieving sales online and/or offline, 68% of businesses rated themselves at a maturity level of 1 or 2, while only 11% rated themselves at the higher maturity level of 4 or 5.</list-item>
</list>
<p>Given the future importance of digital marketing and new entrants who are digital disruptors, larger organizations have introduced digital transformation programmes to help manage these challenges. The approach has been discussed by many management consulting groups.</p>
<p>Why do you want to digitally transform? This is a useful question as it reveals which kind of thinking is being prioritized. Product oriented answers revolve around better products, more efficiencies, and competitive paranoia, while customer oriented answers will be about improving the CX or helping the customer with even better services/products.</p>
<p>Beware, as the sad truth is that most digital transformation programmes are failing. Chap-ter 9 explains why. See also the surprisingly high level of DT failure in the Digital marketing insight box.</p>
<p><bold>Digital marketing insight Most digital transformation is failing</bold></p>
<p>Since digital marketing is enabled through technology, there is a danger that adoption of digital marketing technology will be led by technology decisions. This risk is highlighted in the <italic>Harvard Business Review</italic> article "Digital Transformation Is Not About Technology." Tabrizi, et al. (2019)suggest that businesses will often: "Put the cart before the horse, focusing on a specific technology (&#x0027;we need a machine-learning strategy!&#x0027;)rather than doing the hard work of fitting the change into the overall business strategy first. Not onlyshould they align tech investments with business goals - they should also lean more on insider knowledgethan outside consultants, acknowledge fears about job loss that those insiders may have, develop deep knowledge of how changes will affect customer experience, and use process techniques borrowed from the tech world (experimentation, prototyping, etc.) to facilitate change."</p>
<p><italic>70% Digital Transformation (Projects) Do not Fulfill their Goals.</italic></p>
<p>A recent survey of directors, CEOs, and senior executives found that digital transformation (DT) riskis their no. 1 concern in 2019. Yet 70% of all DT initiatives do not reach their goals. Of the $1.3 trillion that was spent on DT last year, it was estimated that $900 billion went to waste. Why do some DT efforts succeed and others fail? (HBR Tabrizi et al. 2019).</p>
<p>Globally, examples abound of ambitious digital transformation programs wiping out shareholder value and CEO reputations. A study by Everest Group suggests that almost 73% of enterprises failed to provide any business value whatsoever from their digital transformation initiatives (Aggarwal 2021).</p>
<p>Existing operations and legacy technology infrastructure pose a risk to companies that can&#x0027;t transform quickly enough to compete against companiesthat were "born digital," according to research conducted by North Carolina State University&#x0027;s Enterprise Risk Management Initiative and management consulting firm Protiviti Inc (Protiviti 2021).</p>
<p><bold>Post-digital world</bold></p>
<p>The term <italic>post-digital</italic> describes a business world where digital marketing is simply part of marketing. And there is no need to separate digital marketing from marketing. Perhaps Unilever got it right when their head of Comms, Keith Weed, says &#x201C;we are no longer doing digital marketing, but marketing in a digital world&#x201D; (Weed, 2017).<p>
<p>There are different schools of thought when it comes to &#x201C;digital marketing.&#x201D; Essentially, one school says digital cannot and should not be separated from &#x201C;mainstream marketing.&#x201D; As it is naturally integrated into all marketing, digital marketing should never be separate from marketing (Mark Ritson). The second school of thought suggests that some companies benefit from having a centre of digital marketing excellence feeding and supplying the main marketing team/s around the world.</p>
<p>In <italic>Marketing Week</italic> (2021), columnist Mark Ritson suggests that referring to a digital marketing strategy is ridiculous and says: &#x201C;if I ever develop a &#x2018;digital marketing strategy&#x2019; I clearly have no idea what I am doing. For starters, the digital prefix is inherently tactical in nature and execution.&#x201D;</p>
<p>Then we have global corporations like 3M (who have 55,000 products, managed by 100 marketers in 27 business divisions serving both consumer and B2B markets), developing a digital marketing centre of excellence to support the marketing departments. 3M knew &#x201C;Everyone knew they needed to be digital, but everyone was dabbling in it. We weren&#x2019;t building subject matter expertise&#x201D; (Lloyd 2017). So, they built a digital marketing centre of excellence that the 100 marketers can leverage. This specialized team of about 30 - staffed by a selection of internal team members and bolstered with external hiring to fill in the skill gaps - offers everything from SEO to digital content consultation.</p>
<p>We hope we demonstrate in this book that, although digital communications are tactical, prioritizing digital channels, developing a data-driven (insights-driven) business and integrating AI and digital transformation are strategic. They offer opportunities for creating strategic com-petitive advantage through new business and revenue models. Executing digital tactics such as search, content and social media marketing more effectively than competitors to gain visibility, awareness and preference for brands online requires specialized skills. Whether they are in a digital centre of excellence or integrated into a major marketing department does not seem to be critical.</p>
<p><bold>Section 1.4 summary</bold></p>
<p>Some business people get confused with terms related to marketing, digital marketing and e-commerce, intermediaries and influencers. Intermediaries and partners form large parts of 
many organizations&#x2019; plans. Therefore, it is good to know the exact definitions you are working with to scope out your plans.</p>
<p>There are some important digital marketing concepts including lifecycle marketing, con-versational marketing, content marketing, marketing automation, inbound marketing, digital transformation, post-Digital World and the Six Pillars of Success.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S1.5">
<title>1.5 Sostac&#x00AE; planning methodology</title>
<p>PR Smith&#x2019;s SOSTAC&#x00AE; Planning methodology (Smith 2022) is used around the world by thousands of organizations, and we dedicate a full chapter(Chapter 10) to it. We&#x2019;d like to introduce the basic SOSTAC&#x00AE; methodology in the introductory chapter too as it&#x2019;s useful to understand the logic of SOSTAC&#x00AE; plans as it can be applied to any type of plan, including a business plan, a marketing plan, a digital marketing plan, a campaignplan, a digital transformation plan and many other non-marketing plans too:</p>
<list list-type="none">
<list-item>Situation Analysis - where are you now?</list-item>
<list-item>Objectives - where are you going?</list-item>
<list-item>Strategy - how do you get there?</list-item>
<list-item>Tactics (details of strategy italic.e. the marketing mix)</list-item>
<list-item>Actions (how to ensure excellent execution of the tactics - internal marketing)</list-item>
<list-item>Control - how do you know you are getting there (metrics and measurement)</list-item>
<list-item>+ 4Ms men (and women), money (budgets), minutes (time required) and mega data (what data do you need?).</list-item>
</list>
<fig fig-type="figure" id="F1.20" position="float">
<label>FIGURE 1.20</label>
<caption>PR Smith&#x0027;s SOSTAC&#x00AE; Planning Methodology.</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="Fig1_20.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>In this chapter we are going to just open up the first half of SOSTAC&#x00AE; Planning italic.e. SOS. Chapter 10 will explore all of SOSTAC&#x00AE; Planning in more detail. So for now we&#x2019;ll have a brief look at SOS.</p>
<p>You can see a three-minute video explaining SOSTAC&#x00AE; again at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.sostac.org">www.sostac.org</ext-link></p>
<p><bold>Situation analysis</bold></p>
<p>Where are you now? To answer this question you need to do an analysis of each of the following:</p>
<list list-type="none">
<list-item>Customer analysis (includes middlemen/intermediaries as well as end customer analysis)</list-item>
<list-item>Competitor analysis</list-item>
<list-item>Company analysis (your results to date plus strengths and weaknesses)</list-item>
<list-item>Trend analysis (external opportunities and threats affecting your marketplace)</list-item>
</list>
<p>Doing an in-depth Situation Analysis helps you to make an informed decisions (insight- driven decisions). The Situation Analysis will also help you to set better objectives and even better strategies. The analysis can take up to half of your plan (although you might dump a lot of it in the appendices). You need to collect the information all year-round and build a list of sources that answer very specific questions, like &#x201C;who are your ideal customers?&#x201D; We will just mention briefly competition and the emergence of hyper-competition in all markets.</p>
<p><italic>Hyper-competition</italic></p

<p>Once upon a time you competed with well-known competitors in your local marketplace. Then markets became global and you now compete with companies from all over the world in your marketplace. Then it became &#x201C;category-less&#x201D; when competitors from other sectors steal your customers such as Apple competing with Swiss watches. Multiply this by digital disrupters disrupting the status quo so much so that they take your market and close your business as in the case of Sears (once the world&#x2019;s biggest retailer) going into liquidation as Amazon grow and grow.</p>
<p><bold>Digital marketing insight Category-less and disruptors and others deliver hyper-competition Apple watches outsell the Swiss watch industry</bold></p>
<p>Apple outsold the whole of the Swiss watch industry combined. They sold 31 million watches worldwide, while all Swiss watch brands combined sold 21 million watches. Liao (2020). What market are Apple in? Watches, smartphones, technology - do they have categories?</p>
<p><bold>Sears exit v. Amazon growth</bold></p>
<p>From being America&#x0027;s greatest retail company in the 1980s (and arguably the world&#x0027;s biggest retailer), Sears reduced to 3,900 stores back in 2010, then to 1,000 stores in 2018 and filed for bankruptcy in 2018. Sears closed hundreds more storesafter exiting bankruptcy in January 2019, leaving 400 stores open but soon expected to be closer to 100 stores (Shoulberg 2021).</p>
<p><bold>Hyper-competition: you now compete with your customer&#x0027;s last best experience!</bold></p>
<p>Old truth: you are competing with your competitors. New truth: you are competing with the last best experience your customer had. Make brand scores a keyKPI for the full customer-facing organization. Balis2021 HBR</p>
<p><bold>Assessing your marketplace</bold></p>
<p>To effectively plan your digital marketing to predict your results, you need to tap into the wealth of research about current online usage and future trends. In Table 1.2, we summarize a selection of free and paid-for services to help you analyse your online marketplace. In Chapter 2 on digital customers, Chapter 3 on digital models and Chapter 10 on planning, we also explain other aspects of how you can analyse your online marketplace. Meanwhile here&#x2019;s some useful tools to help you start your analysis.</p>
<p><bold>Sloppy digital marketing</bold></p>
<p>Customer service is falling while customer rage is rising. Customer trust is falling while cus-tomer intolerance is rising. Customers will not tolerate time wasting (e.g. slow page downloads, at which we have got worse).</p>
<p>In 2019, Backlinko, a search engine optimization company, analysed five million desktop and mobile pages to learn which factors impact page speed. Key findings:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>Desktop pages were on average taking 10.3 seconds to load.</list-item>
<list-item>Mobile pages were on average taking 27.3 seconds to load.</list-item>
</list>
<p>In 2020, the Nielsen Norman Group (usability global usability experts) observed that &#x201C;in spiteof an increase in Internet speed, webpage speeds have not improved over time.&#x201D; They went on to say that: &#x201C;What is surprising is that, despite today&#x2019;s much faster network speeds and computer processors, people using the internet today are still plagued by the exact same frustration: slow websites&#x201D; (K. Whitenton 2020).</p>
<p><italic>Customer service is falling</italic></p>
<p>Companies just aren&#x2019;t paying enough attention to providing adequate levels of customer serviceby phone, online or in person. For the American consumer, substandard service has become the new normal(Bevis 2019).</p>

<table-wrap id="T1.2" position="float" orientaion="portrait">
<table frame="box" rules="rows">

<thead>
<tr>
<th><italic>Service</italic></th>
<th><italic>Description</italic></th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody><tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle">1 <bold>Google insights tools.</bold></td>
<td align="left" valign="middle">Google is one of the best sources of accurate</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle"> </td>
<td align="left" valign="middle">tools for marketplace analysis including:</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle"> </td>
<td align="left" valign="middle">???? <italic>Google Display Planner</italic> (this Google Ads tool shows relative size and audience of publishers in the Ads programme);</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle"> </td>
<td align="left" valign="middle">???? <italic>Google Trends</italic> - trends in search volume by country - no sign-in required;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle"> </td>
<td align="left" valign="middle">???? <italic>Keyword Planner</italic> - this tool available within AdWords gives estimates of consumer search volumes for different terms.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle">2 <bold>SimilarWeb.</bold></td>
<td align="left" valign="middle">Freemium tool providing traffic ranking of individual sites and their sources of traffic. Works best for larger sites. Alternatives are Alexa and Compete.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle">3 <bold>Nielsen</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.nielsen.com">www.nielsen.com</ext-link>. Paid tool.</td>
<td align="left" valign="middle">Panel service based on at-home and at-work users who have agreed to have their web usage tracked by software. Top rankings on site gives examples of most popular sites in several countries.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle">4 <bold>ComScore</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.comscore.com">www.comscore.com</ext-link>. Paid tool.</td>
<td align="left" valign="middle">A similar panel service to Nielsen, but focus?ing on the US and UK. Publishes free country adoption summaries.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle">5 <bold>Internet or Interactive Advertising</bold></td>
<td align="left" valign="middle">Research focusing on investment in different</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle"><bold>Bureau (IAB)</bold> (US:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.iab.net">www.iab.net</ext-link>UK:</td>
<td align="left" valign="middle">digital media channels, in particular display</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.iabuk.net">www.iabuk.net</ext-link> Europe:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.europe.uk.net">www.europe.uk.net</ext-link>.</td>
<td align="left" valign="middle">ads and search marketing. Paid-for services.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle">6 <bold>Government sources.</bold></td>
<td align="left" valign="middle">Useful government sources include Eurostat (EU: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ofcom.org.uk">www.ofcom.org.uk</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="Statistics.gov.uk">Statistics.gov.uk</ext-link> and Data.gov for the US.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle">7 <bold>Non-government organizations.</bold></td>
<td align="left" valign="middle">Pew Internet Surveys (US: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.pewinternet.org">www.pewinternet.org</ext-link>) and International Telecoms Union (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www. itu.int">www. itu.int</ext-link>).</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle">8 <bold>IMRG</bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.imrg.org">www.imrg.org</ext-link>.</td>
<td align="left" valign="middle">The Internet Media in Retail Group has com?pilations on online e-commerce expenditure in the UK.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle">9 <bold>Alerts</bold> regarding topics, companies, brands</td>
<td align="left" valign="middle">Google Alert, Talkwalker, Awario, social</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle">and individuals.</td>
<td align="left" valign="middle">search, Mention and Ask The Question.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" valign="middle">10 <bold>Influencers.</bold></td>
<td align="left" valign="middle">Crowdbooster.com, Buzzsumo, Followerwonk, Google Analytics.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><italic>Customer rage is rising</italic></p>
<p>Consumers and advertisers are at war. Consumers surrender their personal information, which is then collected and sold back to advertisers for a &#x201C;capitalist micro-assault [that] is, from all directions at all waking moments . . . getting much more intense, focused, targeted, unyielding and galactically more boring,&#x201D; Doug Coupland&#x2019;s apocalyptic words (Caulkin 2016). https:// www.ft.com/content/475789b8-2b2b-11e5-acfb-cbd2e1c81cca</p>
<p><italic>Customer trust is falling</italic></p>
<p>Widespread mistrust of societal institutions and leaders around the world leaves the four institutions - business, government, NGOs and media - in an environment of information bank-ruptcy and a mandate torebuild trust (Edelman Trust Barometer 2021).</p>
<p><bold>Digital marketing success Stop sloppy customer experiences</bold></p>
<p>How many brands do not execute their plans to a high standard? How much money is wasted driving traffic to a website that frustrates visitors? How many service chatbots leave you wanting to pull your hair out? "Develop credibility before raising visibility," italic.e. do your website usability testing beforepromoting the site. Lousy execution not only wastes scarce resources but also destroys the customer experience and, hence, destroys the brand. The ad spend is, effectively, destroying the brand! Mobilize yourteam. Inject purpose and passion (and training) for excellence.</p>
<p>PR Smith 2021 SOSTAC&#x00AE; Guide to your Perfect Digital Marketing Plan</p>
<p>Great plans often fail despite having an in-depthsituation analysis, sensible objectives and a crystal clear strategy followed by clever and creative tactics - on paper, the execution is sloppy. Why? A lack of internal marketing (&#x201C;actions&#x201D; section). The actions section of the plan is often forgotten. Hence, we get a lot of sloppy execution: sloppy websites, sloppy emails, sloppy CRM, sloppy MarTech integration, despite great plans. See Chapter 10 for more on &#x201C;actions&#x201D; - the forgotten piece in many plans.</p>
<p><bold>Digital marketing failure Sloppy Digital Marketing</bold></p>
<p>50% CRM projects failing
82% MarTech Stacks not used properly (Gartner 2020).</p>
<p>Source: </p></<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ft.com/content/42e4ff94-4db9-11e6-8172-e39ecd3b86fc">https://www.ft.com/content/42e4ff94-4db9-11e6-8172-e39ecd3b86fc</ext-link></p>
<p><bold>Digital marketing objectives: PR Smith&#x0027;s 5Ss</bold></p>
<p>One reason why many new businesses, in particularnew startup businesses, go horribly wrong is often because objectives are not clearly agreed upon, and companies keen to get on with it jump straight to tactical tools (such as websites, Google Ads or social media) without first agreeing on clearly defined objectives and razor-sharp strategies</p>.?
<p>You must be clear what you want your digital marketing to deliver. What are the objectives, apart from competitive paranoia? What are the real benefits you want? There are five broad benefits of, reasons for or objectives of digital marketing:</p>
<list list-type="number">
<list-item>Grow sales (through wider distribution, promotion and sales).</list-item>
<list-item>Add value (give customers better service online).</list-item>
<list-item>Build relations. Get closer to customers (by tracking them, asking them questions, creating a dialogue, learning about them).</list-item>
<list-item>Save costs (of service, promotions, sales transactions and administration) and also save time (for both you when you automate some of your marketing plus for your customers who are time poor).</list-item>
<list-item>Enhance the brand online. Reinforce brand values in a digital world where digital can wow customers beyond just better service and into new experiences that excite customers.</list-item>
</list>
<p>We explore objectives in a lot more detail in Chapter 10. For now, we can summarize as the &#x201C;5Ss&#x201D; - Sell, Serve, Speak, Save and Sizzle (PR Smith). These are covered briefly in the next five sections. Once you have defined (and quantified) &#x201C;where you are now&#x201D; (your situation analysis) and &#x201C;where you are going&#x201D; (your objectives), you can then decide &#x201C;how to get there&#x201D; (strategy). First, let us consider objectives</p>.
<p>You should set specific goals for objectives in each of the five areas, as shown in Table 1.3.</p>
</sec>
</body>
</article>





 
